Yeah. So Poland has a widespread view
but you can choose between a pleasant
path to awakening and unpleasant one.
Pleasant usually means through brahma
viharas and unpleasant means through row
insight like like contemplation of
impermanence sickness and death and
ananta. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> And do we really have a choice in this
regard? >> Where does the view come from?
>> Where does the view come from?
>> Where does it come from? And there is a
Polish early Buddhism society for
example which promotes the view.
>> Yeah. But I mean where did they get it
from? Like did they come up with it or
is it sort of based on sutas or
something? >> It's based partially on sutas and it's
>> It's based partially on sutas and it's
based partially on commentaries to
>> I see. Okay. Well putting commentaries
aside as one should um the sutas that
talk about those different forms of
practice are the um sutas refer to
sotapanas at least.
>> Mhm. So it's not just somebody can just
choose how they're going to walk the
path that the Buddha outlaid outlined
for for someone. So it's starts with
with somebody who already has the right
view who already knows what nibbana is
who already sees their own mind because
one of the prerequisites for sauties
developing of chittan nimita seeing the
signs and features of the mind for what
it is and then
in the process of taming their mind that
process might be pleasant unpleasant
might be quick and unpleasant might be
slow and unpleasant and all those
different permutations but that's not
something one can choose. All one can
choose is whether they're going to tame
the mind or not.
So, uh what path you're going to be
walking can only be known in hindsight
after you walked it. You can say, "Oh,
actually that wasn't too bad." Uh
because if it's a matter of choice, why
would anybody choose the unpleasant
path? Everybody would choose the quick and
Everybody would choose the quick and
pleasant if it's actually a matter of
choice. So then there would be only one
way to enlightenment that everybody
would choose. Nobody in their right mind
will want to choose suffering for a long
time towards the enlightenment if there
is an option.
>> And how about putanas?
>> Pujenas have no choice whatsoever. They
don't see the path. That's why they're
putinas. So them choosing what path they
follow is just choosing their own
abstract ideas or what they think the
Buddha might have been teaching. But
that's not seeing the dharma. That's
kind of the main point there. That's why
such sutas they do talk about those
different aspects different emphasis um
of the practice all refer to somebody
who already sees what the practice is
and that's at least the sautana.
So not just that puja doesn't have a
choice uh it doesn't even see the mind.
So the the sole practice of putina
should be establishing themsel in virtue
recollecting the right themes the right
context so to the mind to come up so
that they can see it.
>> Mhm. And that's kind of the beginning of
of the right practice. And that's most
likely not going to feel pleasant
because um again like sure it depends on
an individual as the other sut say
depends on how much dust a person has in
their eyes to begin with but generally
speaking today already dhamma is on like
a like a decline. It's been like two and
a half millennia since the Buddha. Lots
of splits, lots of different views, lots
of different opinions. So you're not
hearing the true dharma when you hear
the dhamma today. It's highly unlikely
you'll be hearing the actual dharma. You
got to be siving through stuff, working
through things, digging through to kind
of discern what the Buddha was teaching.
Which means that most of people today,
most of us probably have a lot more dust
in our eyes because if we didn't, we
would have already been enlightened in
the Buddhist time or shortly afterwards.
So in other words, it's like
you have an option to establish yourself
in virtue, to recognize that mind, the
wild animal, to train it. How is that
going to be felt? That's irrelevant. If
it's important to you before you even
start taming the animal, how it's going
to be felt means you're not going to be
taming the mind. So it's like, oh, I'll
train this this dog only if it's
pleasant. Means you don't really care
about the outcome of the training. You
first and foremost prioritize your own
pleasure and that's why you're put. So
everybody that still wants to choose
their own path for that very reason they
won't be a sabana because they're
refusing to give up their emotional
dependence on pleasure
>> and do brahavihare can help put to
>> no
>> how can they help the the very first
brahihara starts by um practicing the
framework of non ill will towards your
own mind towards your own chitta
protecting the chitta the boundless mind
they don't even see the chitta how can
They practice that which only begins by
seeing the mind.
>> Yes. So as I understand currently
practice of beta is used as kind of
painkiller uh for people.
uh for people.
>> Yes. Management.
>> Mhm.
>> Which you don't need the Buddhas for
that. Basically the Buddhist teaching
for that. Just lots of lots of other
technique methods uh wishful thinking
contemplations u visualizations can help
you with that
>> to an extent but it will not approve the
suffering. Only the dhamma can actually
approve the suffering. But for that you
need to aim for that not just use it as
management of a cover up and sort of making
of a cover up and sort of making
yourself feel better when things are
bad. >> So can it be helpful for people to use
>> So can it be helpful for people to use
this kind of meta as as med?
>> Well, it's not the meta they're using.
>> Meta begins when you see the chitta. If
you don't see the chitta, there is no
practice of brahma viharas for you.
So whatever you do can help or not, it's
not the Buddhist teaching. That's the
point. So we shouldn't be calling meta.
In the same sense, we shouldn't be
calling uh such similar practices that
people refer to as Janna that are not
based on renunciation and seeing the
mind. That's also not Janna. In the same
sense, this is not meta.
>> So regular meditation like anati and
brahma are for
>> high. Exactly. Because all of the any
meditation in the sutras which are
really like practices of composures and
calming of that animal requires you to
see the animal requires you to clearly
discern the mind for what it is. And if
you do so you'll be a sapana.
>> Mhm.
>> So you trying to calm something that you
don't see
it makes no sense.
So uh regular people can they do
contemplations like contemplation of
death contemplation of sickness
contemplation of anata?
>> Absolutely. Yeah. Of course that's
that's that's what they should be doing.
That's what everybody should be doing.
That doesn't change whether you're a lay
person or then later a monk. Those
contemplations remain the same. It's
just probably how much time and quality
of your effort changes like you know as
you change the environment into more
secluded and and monastic and so on. But
the contemplations remain the same.
Yeah. But obviously if as a lay person
you start contemplating those things
without also establishing yourself in
virtue, you're probably going to
experience a lot of disturbances
internally because you're kind of undermining
because you're kind of undermining
everything your current household life
depends on and you don't really have the
means of virtuous behavior providing
container for your mind when it gets
disturbed. So then it's probably better to actually
So then it's probably better to actually
first and foremost start paying
attention to your behavior to your
speech. Uh what kind of topics and
themes and thoughts you choose to dwell
on during the day.
Make sure it's not unh wholesome to the
best of your efforts. And then also bit
by bit start increasing these
contemplations that will undermine your
sense of self, your sense of ownership
and all of that which is sickness,
aging, death, change um things that are
dear to you, things that you find safety
in. uh they will they are otherwise
already basically by not being in your
control by not being able to do anything
about them changing if the change were
to occur.
>> Mhm.
Yeah. So I um
basically uh to make yourself safe you
need to first practice um virtue.
>> Yeah. You need to practice the virtue
like you know you can you can take it on
in that religious dutiful sense but you
actually need to train in it and by that
as we spoke so many times in other talks
means like those principles behind the
precepts you need to not just adhere to
them externally but also internally when
it comes to you choosing the reasons for
saying things for speaking make sure it
doesn't come out of those same
principles of unh wholesome they were
against the precepts and then same about
your when it comes to your thoughts so
like You might not be killing anybody
but your body, but do you wish harm
mentally? And do you allow do do you
allow those thoughts to proliferate? Do
you fuel them? Do you accept them? Or do
you say when they present themselves
through the angry mind, you say, "No, I
I won't allow these thoughts to occupy
me." That's that's already a training effort
That's that's already a training effort
that will not come automatically on its
own simply by you keeping the precepts
externally. So a person needs to train
in virtue to become established in
virtue. Can management technique help in
this? >> Well, failing to practice rightly, it's
>> Well, failing to practice rightly, it's
already the form of management
like you're not you're not you're not
going to overnight some stop managing
and suddenly be on the right path
immediately. So whether you want it or not, you will
So whether you want it or not, you will
be managing. But the problem is when you
start confusing the management for the
practice, for the uprooting, that's when
you're going to stop progressing. If
you're still aiming at the actual
uprooting at the actual immovability at
the actual uh completely being untouched
by the suffering
that aim as it's being developed is
providing a form of management up until
it's developed when it's developed when
you uprooted it then you don't need to
manage but if I tell you yeah management is
but if I tell you yeah management is
fine means any idea that you find
helpful you're going to start confusing
that for practice you think I am
progressing towards sotapati through
doing random stuff that makes me feel
better when I suffer and that's
absolutely not the case. So you need to
aim at the uprooting
and in the process of that aim and
developing that aim improving that aim
you will be manage managing one way or
the other.
>> So maybe is is it good to learn some
management techniques first? Why? If I
just said aiming at the uprooting of
suffering will provide you with
management. Oh,
>> okay.
>> Learning techniques first, it's probably
going to then carry a high risk of being
confused for practice
>> because you're going to find it helpful,
but it's not actually aiming at
uprooting. So, it stops there. Aiming at
uprooting you will also find helpful and
it actually aims at the approoting.
So is practicing virtue and sense
restraint uprooting the suffering?
>> Yes. As I said, if you start applying it
on all these three levels, body, speech,
and mind
>> and taking responsibility not just for
what you do, what you say, but also what
you choose to think and revolve around
during the day and make the effort to
not do that.
Not like, oh, I'm thinking angry
thoughts. It's like the mind is coming
up. The mind's coming. Oh, let me just
go and
concentrate, calm down, watch my
nostrils, do this or that for it to go
away. Yeah, sure, do that. But you
haven't aimed at the uprooting of it. In
other words, you manage the problem
after it came up, but you haven't
understood how can that problem not come up in the
how can that problem not come up in the
first place.
So that's why when you have these
thoughts pressuring you, yes, you
shouldn't be giving in
in accepting those thoughts and fueling
them further. But at the same time, you
shouldn't be trying to get rid of that
state of mind because you need to
understand it.
But if you just want to manage it away
because it's unpleasant, you're not
going to understand anything. So that's
that training.
>> So you sense restraint and then you
watch yourself how you react on this. Uh
well yeah you you you practice sense
restraint and your mind is going to
start your mind is going to start to complain
your mind is going to start to complain
resist
increase the pressure and you don't lose
the sight of that. You don't need to
watch yourself. You need to watch that
background where your mind is and what
pressures it come up with and then make
sure that you're not just blindly trying
to get rid of the discomfort of that
mind because that's what people always
because that's what people always
confuse by not seeing the mind.
They identify the discomfort that the
mind puts on them with the thoughts that
revolve around their day-to-day kind of
attention. So then they like, "Oh, if I
stop thinking, I want to stop thinking
so that the pain at the background goes
away. So that the mind stops hurting,
but that's too much now." So you you
want to not proliferate those thoughts,
but you don't want to get rid of or try
well, you can't get rid of, you're just
going to be covering it up. Um, but you
don't want to deny the state of mind.
You want to know it for what it is. As
Satipatana Suta says, he knows the
lustful mind as lustful mind. He doesn't
say he replaces it with another better
mind. No, he knows it. The knowledge is
the freedom from the state of mind. He
knows the angry mind as angry mind,
elated mind as elated, depressed as
depressed. And that's also what what the more you
And that's also what what the more you
know it uh the more the less uh
identification you're going to have with
that mind because you just see it in its
own state for what it is. and you you
didn't make it that way and you see it
coming and going in a certain way has
nothing to do with you.
>> Wasn't there a sut that you can replace
your thoughts like um
but pieces of of
>> Yeah. But it wasn't about the
replacement of the thoughts. It was
exactly what I'm talking about. So it
was like when you are pressured towards
central thoughts
you don't give into central thoughts and
you can think auba
for your chitta not for replacement of
the thoughts.
So every of those five ways of of of
becoming a master of your thought
>> is is is the threshold the reference
point for that is the state of chitta
behind it.
So you can replace the thoughts as long
as your replacement of the thoughts is
not trying to get rid of the state of
the mind which is what everybody does.
That's why they want to stop thinking.
That's why they want to think positive
thoughts because the mind hurts and they
they refuse to accept that.
>> So why are you replacing the false?
>> Well, you're not replacing them. You're
simply not giving attention. See when
when when when I say a lustful object
present itself, you can choose to see
the beautiful or ugly aspects of the
same thing.
>> So people by default choose the
beautiful but then they were told oh that's bad
but then they were told oh that's bad
you shouldn't do it. Then they want to
force the ugly aspects to get rid of
that state of mind because it hurts. But
that that will not bring any
understanding. So when the choice presents itself to
So when the choice presents itself to
think beautiful aspects of ugly aspects
out of a central mind, you don't try to
get rid of the central mind. You just
make sure you look at the ugly aspects
of the same experience and that's how
the mind learns that the thing that that
the things that the mind is attracted to
are actually disgusting.
You don't want to bring new things a new
state of mind. you want within the same
state to teach it rightly to show it the
uh different aspect of the same thing.
So that's why that suta again does not
apply to anybody randomly puja and
that's why at the end of the suta if you
develop those five ways of thinking
you'll be an arant without anything left
to do. So it's a lot more and certainly
a lot subtler than just oh when it's
this thought think the opposite because
anybody can do that
uneducated completely sort of uh random
not familiar with Buddhism can do that
there is nothing there to understand
just stick to do the opposite just look
at the ugly when it's this look at that
when is that but the whole nuance of the
the state of mind that's bound by by
both and presenting the right aspect to
it that's completely gone that people
Don't see that. That's why that suta is
one of the most misunderstood one. But
if you look at it, it specifically every
one of those refers to the chitta. Does
not just refer to just think this or
that. So if the chitta is lustful within the
So if the chitta is lustful within the
lustful mind, you presented the aspects
of the same thing that are disgusting.
If the chitta is angry within that angry
mind, you don't just choke it and beat
it to stop being angry. No, show it the
nice aspects, the neutral aspects, the
friendly aspects of the same thing that
it hates.
And you might still have a desire for
that chitta to change. But if you don't
give in that blind forcing of change
into chitta because it hurts, just
present it the aspect and wait. That's
like you have to endure the mind on the
right level. So the mind will not
immediately lose the desire when you
present it. say um with the ugly aspect
it will be push it will be pushing for
the beautiful aspects the mind will not
immediately overcome hate if you present
it with the friendly aspect it will be
pushing for the uh hateful aspects but
you don't give into the hateful aspect
you don't choose to proliferate them
sure those thoughts are there but you're
not allowing them the center stage as I
say and then bring the friendliness
aspect but again not forcefully to like
choke the mind with it Just bring it up
and leave it there because that's what
the mind is seeing. It doesn't want to
see it, but you're forcing it to see it
by simply holding it there.
And you stop when the mind sits down and
loses anger or when the mind comes down
and loses passion. And it's like, see
now you didn't beat the passion. You
didn't strangle the mind. You didn't try
to kind of forcefully get out of it, get
it out of it. Uh you simply presented it
the different aspect of the same thing.
And the mind on its own sat down and
lost the desire. So the animal for
itself so oh this is ugly because you
can be telling repeating mantra in your
head all you want. Asuba suba ugly ugly.
The mind doesn't see that. The mind
still sees the beautiful aspects because
that's the only thing you've been
showing it. And whenever you think about
assuba you don't think about it
presenting the ugly to that state of
mind. You want the ugly to replace the
whole experience of that mind. And
that's why suba doesn't work. It might
give you the shock value initially and
you will feel disenchanted.
Do it two or three times in that uh
wrongly like what how I just described
and the mind will find the attractive
within the ugly
and there is no end to that. Like if you
read the vinaya stories there were cases
of monks that they did sexual things
with corpses.
Not because they were perverted from the
start, but because the assuba was not
rooted rightly. So the mind always can
find beautiful even in the ugliest and
vice versa. You could find the ugliest
in beautiful in the most beautiful if
that's what you look for.
So not using the mind as that reference
which need to be taught these things.
People then just try to replace one with
the other and mind will just pick and
choose within the ugly what it likes and
the attraction will remain and come back
on the top and then you might even act
out of it.
>> Mhm.
Um so let's say I am a regular person. I
suffer a lot
and um like um my level of suffering is
barely enabling me to function. And then
I hear that uh during the road to the
right view I'm going to suffer even
more. So how can I decide going that
road? Well, if you want to be free from
suffering
you would do anything that anything that
takes.
If somebody says, "Yeah, freedom from
your ailment is this absolutely
horrible, painful, bitter medicine." But
if you really want to be healthy, you
would take it. Doesn't matter how bad it
is. So if you don't want to take it because
So if you don't want to take it because
it's bitter means you don't really want
to cure yourself.
Oh, I don't like the taste means taste
is more important to you than being free
from pain, from suffering, from dooka.
So it's it's your choice basically.
And the hard part of this is that some
teachers offers the pleasant path.
>> Well, yeah. But as I said before, I mean
it doesn't take great intellect or
supreme wisdom. Uh anybody in this who's
been like say for a few years on this
earth so to speak can ask themselves on
the basis of the limited experience of a
household ordinary average life.
things that are easy to get,
things that are just smooth sailing and
and very very very quickly pleasantly
achieved or things that are hard to get that you
or things that are hard to get that you
have to work for, endure, really put in
effort. Which of those things are
usually more valuable, more longlasting,
and have greater impact?
>> So, everybody knows an answer to that
the answer to that question.
And the Buddhist practice is no
exception to that principle. If
anything, it's even more of that
principle because freedom from suffering
obviously it's the most important
fundamental thing. So it's certainly not
going to be easy sailing.
So the practice remains the same. And
even when those pleasant parts were
described in the sutas, they were not
different parts. They were the same
parts that just for some people were not
as unpleasant.
But that's not something you can
predecide. The reason those paths were
not ask yourself if I were to become
celibate tomorrow. That's the path.
If I suffer, will I suffer or will I not
suffer? >> Yeah, you will suffer.
>> Yeah, you will suffer.
>> There you go. You are the type that
needs the suffering path.
Just set yourself with the right path
from the sutras and see if your mind
resists or not. And that will then you
can tell which category you will fall
in. But there were people back in the day
But there were people back in the day
that just said, "Oh yeah, this is
unsuitable for me to engage in sexual
intercourse. Oh, it's unsuitable for me
to do these things." And they abandoned
it. And obviously the mind didn't even
suffer. But as I said, probably most of
those people were were done by now. they
would have already completed their work
if they had that little dust in their
eyes. But yeah, maybe as I said before, maybe
But yeah, maybe as I said before, maybe
you are the lucky one. Maybe you are
really have little dust in your eyes.
Set yourself with the eight precepts.
Commit to the path and see if your mind
doesn't suffer, great, you are the one
who is on the pleasant path.
But this whole idea of all pleasant path
is what I choose to do pleasantly for
the enlightenment. That's absolutely
ridiculous. The path is the same
unchanged. Some people will suffer a lot
on account of it. Some people will
suffer not so much. Some people won't
suffer at all. But the path remains the
same. Some people will have to walk a
long time the same path do the same
thing. Some people not so long. Some
people can do it very quickly. But it's
the path is the same.
Yeah. And and um some people say that
for example abandoning romantic
relationships are spiritual bypassing
because you are doing it out of fear.
So well obviously those people are not
concerned about their own well-being and
being free from suffering and samsara.
So it's not much to say to them. If they
think spiritual rel romantic
relationships are a path well good luck
to them. Yeah usual logic uh goes like
this like you cannot abandon things if
you really fear them. Uh so you have to
like abandon fear first and like
engage with it so you can prove yourself
that you can engage without fear.
>> That does not seem very logical because
the sole reason you wouldn't be
abandoning those things is because of
fear. So how can you abandon fear if you
just keep giving into fear and
supporting it and fueling it and acting
out of it?
So ask yourself which is more
frightening to continue romantic
relationship or to break all ties and
live alone which is scarier.
>> I guess it depends on on the people.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Of course everything depends
on the individuals like not everybody
starts from the same position but as I
said the practice and the principles
remain unchanged.
So, >> so is fear a good motivator to abandon
>> so is fear a good motivator to abandon
the world?
>> Yes. If it's obviously uh
recognized rightly
like you should have fear, you should be
afraid of suffering. You should be
afraid of liability to suffer. That's
how the sutas describe like a young man
basically recognizes that his situation
like, "Oh, I am prey to suffering.
In other words, even if nothing
unpleasant is happening now, the fact
that it could
shows that oh, you are within the domain
of suffering. You are its prey.
Suffering will get you at some point and
that in itself recognition is suffering.
So if you develop fear towards that
liability, then you will be practicing
rightly.
And what with case with someone who
let's say wants to have a romantic
relationship from one side and from
other side he is afraid of them. Well,
he needs to uh make a choice.
So if you want to have a romantic
relationship, find safety in connecting
with others in um like in the world
um you can do that but you can't
practice the dharma at the same time.
So it's either or.
So ask yourself which is which is more
important which is which has greater
impact. Um which one of those two offers a
Um which one of those two offers a
temporary superficial sense of safety
which one of those two offers a lasting
sense of safety like when you're free
from samsara develop right view you do
it once and for all.
So ask yourself those questions think
about them and then make a choice.
Nobody forces you to practice. Nobody
forces you to do anything.